I'll Become My Own Hope
and Live a Happy Life
Summer has gone, autumn has arrived
since we last spoke.
Time flies.
Time moves slowly when we're young,
but how is it now?
Does it not go by faster?
Similarly, the same incident
can reflect differently
depending on the person,
their age and circumstances.
Time moves slowly
when we're waiting for something.
But when we're engaged in an activity
we like, it goes by fast.
Hence the old saying :
When times are hard,
a single day feels like
the passage of three autumns.
It indicates that a single day
feels like three years.
But when we're happy, what do we say?
Do we not say, "Ten years
feels like a single day"?
It feels as if only a day had gone by.
The same single day, single year
can go by fast or feel like an eternity
based on your state of mind.
Hence the state of mind
we're in is important.
While looking at the same object,
some say it's good, others say it's bad.
While looking at the same behavior,
some say it's good, others say it's evil.
Some say a certain thing is well done,
others say it's poorly done.
We see young people posting
comments on the internet.
Their opinions range from one extreme
to another on a single subject.
There are varying points of views.
"Buddha mentioned that
our distinctions don't exist
in the objects/matters themselves.
Our distinctions -
long, short, wide, narrow,
big, small, fast, slow, heavy, light,
right, wrong, correct, incorrect, good,
evil - are created within our mind. "
Hence we say, "Everything
depends on the mind".
This means that whether we consider
a person's behavior to be good or bad
all comes from the mind.
I'm not saying that thinking
a certain thing is gold makes it gold.
That's not what I mean by it.
I'm not saying it'll rain
if you want it to rain,
or it would clear up if you want it to.
When it's raining,
one would think it's good weather,
another would think it's bad.
Such distinctions come from the mind.
All judgments arise within the mind.
Hence whether your husband is a good
person or not depends on your own mindset.
It does not depend on your husband.
And yet we don't think this way.
We make up our mind
on things and objectify.
We consider people as bad within our own
minds and state that they are bad people.
Who are we saying requires change here?
Should I be the one that changes
or the other person?
We think the other person should change,
as he is a bad person.
Once you realize all is in the mind,
you'll know that
it all originates from your mind.
Once you realize, you should change
your mind, your thoughts.
Buddha said, "We create our own
happiness and unhappiness.
The truth is that they don't
come from others."
They don't come from the outside,
they come within you.
If you are feeling unhappy, it is
because you want to feel unhappy.
Does this make you feel falsely accused?
Happy people make
happiness for themselves.
If you're 30 and unmarried,
it's for you to decide whether
it's a good thing or a bad thing.
The fact that you're 30 and unmarried
itself is neither a good thing
nor a bad thing. It is what it is.
Then is it correct to say "I failed to
marry yet"? It's incorrect to say so.
You're bounding yourself
to your own conditions.
You're ultimately making yourself unhappy.
If you look from a positive standpoint,
the same thing can be a good thing.
And yet we generally seek things
from a negative perspective.
Who becomes unhappy to be negative?
It is you that becomes unhappy.
If you see things from a positive
standpoint, you become happy.
Let's say you have a mother-in-law
that is 80 years old.
The fact itself is neither a good thing
nor a bad thing.
If you think 'She still hasn't passed
away', then it becomes a bad thing.
You're saying it's troublesome
to take care of her.
Hence you'd be putting yourself
in a miserable situation.
But if you say, 'She is still alive
and well', it becomes a good thing.
As you see, whether it's a good or
bad thing to have her around is up to you.
But how do we think of things?
We say we're unhappy with
those that are still with us,
we're also unhappy with
those that have passed away.
Married people should be
happy with their marriage,
unmarried people should be happy
that they are unmarried.
And yet unmarried people are
envious of those that are married,
married people are
envious of those that aren't.
We always look at things
negatively and are pessimistic.
Hence we are in agony throughout life.
Happy people always
have a positive outlook.
Life should be enjoyable.
Happy people aren't necessarily happy
because their lives are perfect.
They have a positive outlook in life.
Unhappy people aren't unhappy
because their lives are difficult.
They see things in a negative way.
People with kids are
unhappy with their kids,
people with a husband are
unhappy with their husband.
People without a husband are unhappy
for not having a husband,
for being lonely and childless.
It's not your circumstance
that needs to change.
It's you that should change
- you should change
your negative outlook to a positive one.
Whether you are happy or unhappy
depends on how you see and think things.
Hence our destiny does not lie in the
hands of god, previous lives nor fate.
Our destiny lies in our own hands. It
depends on our own outlook towards life.
Hence we are the masters of our lives.
In other words, we seek after
the bluebird of happiness.
We climb over mountains
to chase after it,
but realize it was under
our very own roof all along.
We seek for happiness from
outside and never find it.
Only when we search within
ourselves can we find it.
It all depends on our state of mind.
Hence today's first topic is about taking
ownership of your life to be happy.
I should be my own hope and live happily.
Hope doesn't come from elsewhere,
it comes from within.
There is no other master of my destiny.
I am the master of my own destiny.
If you look at the so-called
successful people,
they lived as masters of their lives
and overcame all kinds of obstacles.
Those that are unsuccessful get
beaten down and live life in agony.
While going through the same
experience, some get taken down,
others own it and enrich
themselves through it.
And yet those that fail claim they went
down under harsh circumstances.
All things that happen in life
are neither good nor bad.
If you take experiences as life
lessons, they enrich your life.
You become more capable as a person them.
If you hold onto them as scars within
you, you end up stressed and in pain.
And yet we still think we'll become
happy once circumstances change.
We mistakenly think that happiness is
something that is given to us by someone else.
We still chase after the
bluebird of happiness.
We waste our precious days waiting
for someone to give us hope.
From now on, you are
the master of your own life.
I make myself happy,
not someone else.
Hope comes within myself,
not from elsewhere.
We should seek the path within ourselves.
Having said that, we are
accustomed to our old ways.
During dharma talks you'd think,
'Yeah, I'm the problem'
But once things happen you'd
say, 'You're the problem!'
We revert back to old ways
as if a spring uncoils right back. Why?
We've been thinking, speaking
and acting a certain way for so long.
We unconsciously go back
to our old ways instantly.
Hence it's important to first acknowledge the fact that
all paths are within oneself.
We call this 'seeing the path', 'knowing
the path', 'understanding the path'.
It means we know that happiness is within
ourselves, not given from elsewhere.
It's natural for those that
don't know the path to get lost.
However, even those that do know
the path sometimes get lost.
We keep reverting back
to our old ways. Why?
It's because we've grown a habit of thinking,
speaking and acting a certain way.
As our subconscious mind is
formed a certain way,
our actions just come out a certain way.
Once it happens we should think,
'Ah, I've fallen back to
my old habits again. I was not awake.'
We should realize our faults
and come back to seek the path.
We should repeat this process many times.
Only through practice
and failure of realizing and seeking
the path can we strive towards success.
We call this practice.
We call this process
spiritual cultivation.
Spiritual cultivation refers to walking
the path to an awakened state.
Once you're there,
you no longer revert back to your old ways
regardless of your surroundings.
Once there, there is nothing
else to learn or practice.
It can be said that you are enlightened.
There are three stages to enlightenment:
seeing the path, walking the path,
and reaching the path.
In short, we should first
acknowledge the truth.
As of now, we are still
ignorant of the truth.
Hence we need to acknowledge it first.
Second, knowing the truth is not enough
as we revert back to our old ways.
We get angry, we get greedy, we start
nagging others without knowing it.
Practice is needed to fix this.
We need to follow the path.
And yet this requires
many trials and errors.
It requires an ongoing process
of slips and failures.
That process of practice
refers to walking of the path.
The effort to be aware and
present at every moment,
and to reflect on failures
and pledging not to fail again -
this we call sincere practice.
Only through reflecting and renewing
your resolution can we reach our goal.
Only then can happiness become ours.
Repeat after me :
I will live happily by
becoming my own hope.
I will live happily
as the master of my life.
Who decides whether
you live happily or not?
(Audience ) I do.
Not your husband, not your kids,
not your parents, not the world.
It is you that decides.
Hence you have both the right and
responsibility to live a happy life.
If you blame other people and neglect
your life, you can't help be unhappy.
Therefore do not neglect
your life irresponsibly.
Happiness shouldn't take effort.
Do you understand?
Living a happy life doesn't mean
you should be
overwhelmingly happy on a daily basis.
Living a happy life means
you are not in agony.
Do squirrels in the mountains live
happily or not? Neither, they just live.
(Audience Laughter)
And let compared to those people that are
unhappy, they are in a much better place.
When we're held against our will, we envy
the birds for being able to fly away.
When we're unhappy, we
become less than animals.
We should at least live as happy
as animals, should we not? We should.
And yet most of us are
living less than animals.
To be better off than animals,
we should live happily.
The bare minimum should be to live as is.
It's good to live
a little happier than that,
but we're not saying
we should be happy every day.
But we shouldn't live in agony.
We shouldn't be unhappy and pessimistic.